Guide to the Mitchell-Tiffany Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Mitchell-Tiffany family papers
1803-1932
MS 701
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
21
(31 boxes, 8 folios)
The major figures in these papers are Alfred and Annie O. Tiffany Mitchell, whose correspondence, diaries, writings, financial accounts, photographs and other memorabilia make up the major part of the papers. Of particular interest is a long series of letters from their daughter, Charly Tiffany Mitchell Jeans. During her years at Bryn Mawr College, 1894-1898, her letters describe her education and life there. After her marriage in 1907 to the English philosopher, James Jeans, she wrote of her life in England with particularly graphic letters during the first World War. Nine branches of the family are represented in the remaining papers by scattered items of correspondence, clippings, household accounts, financial papers and assorted memorabilia. The sermons of Alfred Mitchell (1790-1831) make up the largest single portion of this section; the papers of the most prominent family member, Louis Comfort Tiffany, include only a small amount of correspondence, clippings and a drawing. His letters to his sister, Annie O. Mitchell, are in the Mitchell correspondence. The papers also include extensive genealogies, family histories and photographs of the United States and places abroad visited by Alfred Mitchell.
Mitchell, Alfred, 1832-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Mitchell-Tiffany families between 1945 and 1978.
Arrangement
Arranged in six series: I. Correspondence of Alfred and Annie O. Mitchell. II. Financial, Legal and Household Papers. III. Diaries and Writings. IV. Personal and Biographical Materials. V. Papers of Other Family Members. VI. Photographs and Artifacts.
Scope and Contents
The Mitchell-Tiffany Papers consist of correspondence, financial and legal papers, household accounts, diaries, writings, memorabilia and photographs. They are arranged in six series: I CORRESPONDENCE OF ALFRED AND ANNIE O. MITCHELL, II FINANCIAL, LEGAL AND HOUSEHOLD PAPERS OF ALFRED AND ANNIE O. MITCHELL, III DIARIES AND WRITINGS OF ALFRED AND ANNIE O. MITCHELL, IV PERSONAL AND BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS OF ALFRED AND ANNIE O. MITCHELL, V PAPERS OF OTHER FAMILY MEMBERS.
The collection is divided into two major portions: the papers of Alfred and Annie O. Mitchell and the papers of other family members. Alfred and Annie O. Mitchell are the central figures of the collection; the materials found in Series V were preserved largely as a result of Alfred and Annie O. Mitchell's efforts to collect materials relating to the history of the family. Annie O. Mitchell outlived her husband by 27 years, and perhaps for this reason it is her papers which form the core of the collection. The strongest feature of the collection is that the materials, covering the period from 1803 to 1932, present an interesting perspective on American family life during several generations. The greatest concentration of material covers the late nineteenth century.
Dates and notations found throughout the collection, with the exception of those found in brackets, were made by family members during their preliminary processing of the collection and have been retained for the assistance which they might provide the researcher.
Series I, CORRESPONDENCE OF ALFRED AND ANNIE O. MITCHELL, is comprised almost entirely of incoming letters, the great majority of which are addressed to Annie O. (Tiffany) Mitchell. The correspondence covers the years from 1861 to 1932 and is divided into two sections.
The first, Select Correspondence, is arranged in alphabetical order by the name of the author. The individuals in this section are primarily family members or close friends, some of whom Annie O. (Tiffany) Mitchell apparently met during her school days. The most extensive groups of letters are from the two daughters, Alfreda (Mitchell) Bingham and Charly Tiffany (Mitchell) Jeans and their husbands. There are also a substantial number of letters from Annie O. Mitchell's parents, Charles and Harriet Tiffany; her brother, Louis Comfort Tiffany and his wife Mary; her aunt Lydia B. Young; and Alfred Mitchell's brother, Donald Grant Mitchell. These letters not only contain detailed information about the two branches of the family, but also provide insights into the social history of the period.
The most active correspondent in the collection was the Mitchells' youngest daughter, Charly Tiffany (Mitchell) Jeans. She attended Bryn Mawr College from 1894 to 1898, and only a few years after her marriage to James Hopwood Jeans (later Sir James Jeans) she returned with him to his native England. As a result of these extended separations from her family, there are many more letters from her in the collection than from any other single correspondent. The letters which she wrote to her parents from Bryn Mawr College are of particular interest because of the information which they contain about life at a woman's college at the turn of the century. Charly also wrote to her mother regularly throughout the first World War and while the letters do not mention very many specific events in detail, they do reveal something of her personal attitudes toward the war and particularly the German Zeppelin raids. In several of the letters from this period entire paragraphs have been erased. This may be as a result of war-time censorship, for in one letter Charly suggests that some of her letters may not be reaching America because of the censorship.
The remaining correspondence is essentially conversational and records primarily family news. There are, however, two letters from Hiram Bingham III which are of particular note. The first, dated 1924 Mar 28, relates his meeting with President Coolidge to discuss a keynote speech which Bingham was scheduled to make at the Republican state convention in Connecticut. The letter was written at the height of the Teapot Dome scandal while Bingham was Lieutenant Governor of Connecticut. In the letter he states that he has just heard of the resignation of Attorney General Harry M. Daugherty. The second letter, dated 1926 Mar 5, was written while Bingham was Senator from Connecticut, and discusses his work with the President's Aircraft Board and Dwight Morrow. For more material relating to Hiram and Alfreda (Mitchell) Bingham, see the Hiram Bingham Family Papers, MS Group No. 81.
The second section, General Correspondence, contains a few letters written by Alfred and Annie O. Mitchell, letters received from unidentified or less significant individuals, and less substantive letters received on special occasions. Letters are arranged chronologically within each of these categories. Letters written by Alfred and Annie O. Mitchell to other family members are filed with that individual's papers in Series V, PAPERS OF OTHER FAMILY MEMBERS. Only one folder of additional outgoing letters is filed in the General Correspondence of Series I. Scattered letters received from various individuals, primarily friends and acquaintances, span the years 1857 to 1932, with the largest concentration in the years 1862 to 1867. The single folder of invitations includes an invitation to the opening ceremonies for the Brooklyn Bridge (1883). At the end of General Correspondence there are three folders of letters received on the engagement of Alfred and Annie O. Mitchell (1871), and on the deaths of Charles L. Tiffany (1902) and Alfred Mitchell (1911).
There is some correspondence of a purely financial or legal nature in Series II, and the correspondence of family members other than Alfred and Annie O. Mitchell will be found in Series V. A few letters addressed to Alfred Mitchell on the subject of family history will be found in Series V, in the folders labeled "Papers used by Mary E. Perkins in the preparation of Chronicles of a Connecticut Farm, 1769-1905.
Series II, FINANCIAL, LEGAL AND HOUSEHOLD PAPERS OF ALFRED AND ANNIE O. MITCHELL, consists of financial statements, statements of receipts and disbursements, financial and legal correspondence, legal documents, stock certificates, notices of stockholders meetings, and various household accounts, receipts, and memoranda. The items in this series are arranged chronologically by type of material.
The series begins with wills of Alfred and Annie O. Mitchell. The first large group of materials--agreements, legal briefs, and financial statements concerning the Annie O. Mitchell Trust--is extensive but incomplete, covering the years 1911 to 1935. Statements of receipts and disbursements consist of financial reports concerning various properties owned by Annie O. Mitchell. The statements were prepared by her nephew, Donald Grant Mitchell, Jr., who acted as her agent. They cover the years 1919 to 1932. The next major group of materials consists of correspondence, legal documents, and financial statements relating to the estate of Charles L. Tiffany (1902-1929), the Burnett Y. Tiffany Trust (1902-1932), the Louise H. Tiffany Trust (1906-1909), the Annie O. Mitchell Trust for Alfreda M. Bingham and Charly T. M. Jeans (1917-1931), and the Annie O. Mitchell Tiffany Trust for Olivia Jeans (1925-1927). Throughout this section of the series are letters from Robert Thorne, legal counsel for Annie O. Mitchell, and from Charles L. Tiffany II, as an official of Tiffany and Company.
The Mitchell household papers include stock certificates, stockholders' notices, household account books, records of servants' wages in Jamaica and New York, receipts, bills and inventories. These materials relate to homes in New York City, Salem, Connecticut, and Port Antonio, Jamaica, and to trips to Europe and Japan.
Series III, DIARIES AND WRITINGS OF ALFRED AND ANNIE O. MITCHELL, contains diaries, memoranda books, articles and notebooks, arranged by author and by type of material. Items are arranged chronologically within each category of material.
Annie O. Mitchell's papers in this series consist of diaries, memoranda books and notes on family history. The diaries cover the years 1865-1867, 1896, and 1911-1929. The early diaries contain periodic entries of various lengths recording events of personal interest. The later diaries, however, contain only brief entries noting daily activities. The chronological gap between the two sets of diaries is partially filled by a series of memoranda books, dated 1867 to 1895. The content of these memoranda books varies from book to book; some contain only financial notations while others include notes of daily activities. One folder of notes on family history completes Annie O. Mitchell's writings.
Alfred Mitchell's writings include one diary volume, several articles and a Civil War regimental roll book. His diary covers the years 1906 to 1910, with very brief entries concerning weather conditions and daily activities. The articles include manuscripts concerning his stay on a guano island and the Guatemala coffee growing business; his translation of a French novel, clipped from Hearth and Home, a periodical edited by his brother Donald G. Mitchell and Harriet Beecher Stowe; and a notebook and clippings concerning the plants of Jamaica, entitled "A Natural History of the Folly." Alfred Mitchell's papers also include a regimental roll-book listing soldiers involved in the assault on Port Hudson, Louisiana, during the Civil War.
During the years 1911 and 1912 Annie O. Mitchell employed a secretary named Miss Miller, who kept memoranda books recording the Mitchells' daily activities. The two volumes are included here because they provide a diary-like account of their lives during these two years, including the death of Alfred Mitchell.
Series IV, PERSONAL AND BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS OF ALFRED AND ANNIE O. MITCHELL, is comprised of school catalogs, student compositions, notebooks, passports, invitations, gift lists, visitors' cards and newspaper clippings. These papers are arranged by individual and by type of material, and provide general personal information about Alfred and Annie O. Mitchell. Of special interest are student compositions of Annie O. Tiffany and obituaries of Alfred Mitchell.
Series V, PAPERS OF OTHER FAMILY MEMBERS, contains letters, legal documents, financial records, sermons, writings and newspaper clippings pertaining to more than twenty-five relatives of Alfred and Annie O. Mitchell. The papers of individual family members are arranged alphabetically by name, with letters filed with the recipient's papers. Letters written by Alfred and Annie O. Mitchell, for example, may be found in the papers of Alfreda M. Bingham, Charly T. M. Jeans, and several other family members. The individuals whose papers are contained in this series are members of the Mitchell, Tiffany, Woodbridge, Mumford, Bingham, Jeans, Perkins, Young and Thatcher families. The biographical sketches and genealogical chart provided in the register will aid in identifying individuals and relationships.
As a result of Alfred Mitchell's efforts to collect information concerning his ancestors, the Mitchell family is the most fully represented family in this series. The papers of Alfreda (Mitchell) Bingham and Charly T. (Mitchell) Jeans include correspondence, juvenile papers and wedding aanouncements. The largest group of materials in the series consists of the sermons of the Reverend Alfred Mitchell (1790-1831), spanning the years 1821 to 1831. The papers of Donald Grant Mitchell (1822-1908) include correspondence, financial and legal papers, twenty-one issues of Hearth and Home (1869), maps of the Edgewood development, a report on East Rock park in New Haven, and newspaper clippings. His literary papers are in the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Other Mitchell family members represented in this series include Louis Mitchell (1826-1881), Lucretia M. (Woodbridge) Mitchell (1794-1839), Stephen Mix Mitchell (1743-1835), Stephen Mix Mitchell II (1818-1839), and Walter Mitchell (1777-1849). The papers of Charles Lewis Tiffany (1812-1902) contain correspondence, bills and receipts, a brief published biography, newspaper clippings and obituaries. There is a small amount of material relating to Charles L. Tiffany II (1878-?), Harriet (Young) Tiffany (1813-1897), and Louis Comfort Tiffany (1848-1933).
The series also contains some genealogical material, including an annotated copy of the Woodbridge Record, other genealogical records of the Woodbridge family, and materials used by Mary E. Perkins in preparing Chronicles of a Connecticut Farm, 1769-1905.
Series VI, PHOTOGRAPHS, contains seven folders of photographs, two photograph scrapbooks of Alfreda Mitchell, fourteen photograph albums of Alfred Mitchell, and eight albums of photographs by professional photographers. Most of the individual photographs are professional portraits of Mitchell and Tiffany family members. Alfred Mitchell's portraits of his immediate family, other relatives, and friends--particularly in albums titled "Portraits" and "Family History" (volumesI-V)--reveal his talents as an amateur photographer. Other albums document the family's many trips to Europe, the Caribbean, Egypt, Mexico, and the southern and western United States. Professional photographs include the "Millet collection of Japanese photos," numerous cartes de visite (by Mathew Brady, among others), and cabinet photographs.
The Mitchell-Tiffany Papers have been donated to the Yale University Library over a period of more than thirty years. In 1945 Walter L. Mitchell donated a small collection of Mitchell family papers, including: letters and papers, 1803-1868, of Walter Mitchell, Donald Grant Mitchell and other family members; sermons of Reverend Alfred Mitchell; and the "Woodbridge Record." This collection was incorporated with the Mitchell-Tiffany Papers after the bulk of the present collection was donated by Woodbridge Bingham in 1967. Additional papers were given by Woodbridge Bingham and Alfred Mitchell Bingham at various times prior to and during 1978.
Researchers may wish to consult the registers for the following related collections:
Alfred Bingham Papers, MS Group No. 148: papers of Alfred Mitchell Bingham (b. 1905), relating primarily to his career as editor of Common Sense.
Bingham Family Papers, MS Group No. 81: include papers of Hiram Bingham III (1875-1956) and Alfreda (Mitchell) Bingham (1874-1967), which contain some correspondence and papers relating to Alfred and Annie O. Mitchell.
Yale Peruvian Expedition Papers, MS Group No. 664: expeditions led by Hiram Bingham III in 1911, 1912 and 1914-15; papers include journals and writings of Bingham and some correspondence from Annie O. Mitchell.
Donald Grant Mitchell Papers, Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
See also, Union Manuscript Catalogue, under the following headings: Bingham, Alfred Mitchell (b. 1905), Bingham, Hiram (1875-1956), Mitchell, Alfred (1832-1911), Mitchell, Donald Grant (1822-1908), Mitchell, Lucretia Mumford (Woodbridge) (1792-1839), Mitchell, Stephen Mix (1743-1835), Mitchell, Walter (1777-1849), Tiffany, Louis Comfort (1848-1933), and Tiffany & Company.
Biographical / Historical
Alfred Mitchell was the youngest son of the Reverend Alfred Mitchell and Lucretia M. (Woodbridge) Mitchell. When the Reverend Mitchell died on December 19, 1831, his wife accepted the invitation of her uncle, Judge Elias Perkins, to occupy his home, the Shaw mansion in New London. It was here that Alfred Mitchell was born on April 1, 1832. His mother died on March 29, 1839, and his eldest brother, Stephen Mix Mitchell (1818-1839), died a few weeks later as a result of pulmonary disease. In the summer of 1839 Gen. William Williams became the guardian of the Mitchell children.
Alfred Mitchell was a member of the class of 1854 at Yale College but left without taking a degree because of poor health. He was later awarded an honorary degree by the university. As a young man Alfred Mitchell engaged in the whaling industry in Honolulu and the ship chandlery business in New York. These business enterprises, neither of which appears to have been successful, required travel to the Sandwich (Hawaiian) Islands. In 1861 Alfred Mitchell returned from the Sandwich Islands to enlist in the Union Army. He took a commission as a captain in the Thirteenth Connecticut Regiment, which was transported to Louisiana and became part of the Army of the Gulf of Mexico. Alfred Mitchell was promoted to the rank of Major in May, 1863, and ultimately served on the staff of General Henry W. Birge.
After the war Mitchell moved to California where he worked in gold mining for several years, without financial success. On his return to the East he traveled to Guatemala to investigate the prospects for entering the coffee business, but his interests in Guatemala never seem to have advanced beyond the preliminary stages.
On April 27, 1871, Alfred Mitchell married Annie O. Tiffany, daughter of Charles Lewis Tiffany, founder of a prominent jewelry business. Alfred Mitchell became a trustee of Tiffany and Company but appears to have engaged in few, if any, other business activities after his marriage.
Annie Olivia Tiffany was born on November 27, 1844, in New York, the daughter of Charles Lewis Tiffany and Harriet Olivia A. (Young) Tiffany. She attended the Wheaton Female Seminary in Norton, Massachusetts, and married Alfred Mitchell on April 27, 1871. After their marriage, the Mitchells established residences at the Mitchell family home in New London, New York City, and, after 1900, their estate "The Folly" at Port Antonio, Jamaica. They also owned property at Salem, Connecticut, which had formerly been in the Woodbridge family. They traveled frequently throughout Europe, Egypt and Japan. Alfred and Annie O. Mitchell had two daughters, Alfreda Mitchell and Charly Tiffany Mitchell.
Alfred Mitchell died at Port Antonio on April 27, 1911, at the age of 79. After her husband's death Mrs. Mitchell spent most of her time at home in Florida. She died in Miami on January 2, 1937, at the age of 92.
OTHER FAMILY MEMBERS
Alfreda (Mitchell) Bingham was born in New York on December 29, 1874, the daughter of Alfred and Annie O. (Tiffany) Mitchell.
On November 20, 1900, she married Hiram Bingham III, son of Rev. Hiram and Minerva Clarissa (Brewster) Bingham. Seven sons were born of the marriage: Woodbridge, born November 20, 1901; Hiram IV, born July 17, 1903; Alfred Mitchell, born February 20, 1905; Charles Tiffany, born August 31, 1906; Brewster, born September 1, 1908; Mitchell, born November 20, 1910; and Jonathan Brewster, born April 24, 1914.
Alfreda and Hiram Bingham were divorced on March 27, 1937. Alfreda Bingham later married Henry Gregor, a pianist and composer born in Moscow of German and Russian parents. She died on August 27, 1967.
Charly Tiffany (Mitchell) Jeans was born in New York on January 22, 1877, the daughter of Alfred and Annie O. (Tiffany) Mitchell.
Charly Mitchell attended Bryn Mawr College from 1894 to 1898. In 1907 she married James Hopwood Jeans (later Sir James Jeans) and in 1909 returned with him to England. James and Charly (Mitchell) Jeans had one daughter, Olivia Jeans. Charly Jeans seems to have suffered from poor health throughout her adult life and died in 1934 at the age of 57.
Reverend Alfred Mitchell, the youngest son of Stephen Mix Mitchell (1743-1835), was born in Wethersfield, Connecticut, on May 22, 1790. He graduated from Yale College in 1809, and then studied theology with the Reverend Dr. Ebenezer Porter, of Washington, Connecticut. When Dr. Porter accepted a professorship at Andover Theological Seminary in March, 1832, Alfred Mitchell accompanied him and finished the year with the senior class.
Mitchell then preached for a short time to a congregation in Bridge-water, Massachusetts. In 1813 he began a pastorate at the Second Congregational Church at Chelsea on the Landing in Norwich, Connecticut. Mitchell was ordained and installed on October 27, 1814, the ordination sermon being preached by Dr. Porter (a copy of which is included in the collection). His prosperous pastorate was terminated by his death, after an illness of eight weeks, on December 19, 1831, at the age of 41.
On January 16, 1815, Reverend Mitchell married Lucretia Mumford Woodbridge, the second daughter of Nathaniel Shaw and Elizabeth (Mumford) Woodbridge, of what is now Salem, Connecticut. She died on March 29, 1839, at the age of 45. Their marriage produced four daughters and five sons. Two daughters and a son died in infancy. The eldest son, Stephen Mix Mitchell, born April 13, 1818, was a member of the Amherst College class of 1838 but withdrew because of pulmonary disease, which proved fatal in 1839. Donald Grant Mitchell (1822-1908) was the second son, and the youngest son was Alfred Mitchell (1832-1911).
Donald Grant Mitchell was born in Norwich, Connecticut on April 12, 1822, the son of Rev. Alfred Mitchell and Lucretia M. (Woodbridge) Mitchell. He graduated from Yale in 1841, where, in his last year, he was editor of the Yale Literary Magazine. After graduation he moved to the family farm in Salem, Connecticut, and continued his literary work. In 1843 he was awarded a silver medal (by the New York Agricultural Society) for his plans of farm buildings. From the autumn of 1844 until January, 1845, he worked as a clerk to Joel W. White, consul to Liverpool. Because of a pulmonary weakness he retired to the milder climate of the island of Jersey. From March, 1845, to August, 1846, he traveled, much of the time on foot, through Britain and Europe.